super excited for this conversation i
have to say
the same to you thank you yeah i've been
spending the last week and a half in
particular
both your books cynthiaism with jan
sodoquist and
digital libido have been really
illuminating
reads i've really enjoyed them i so
thank you for writing them thank you
they're
two-thirds of a trilogy and the working
title of the trilogy is
the exodology and um
working on the third book tentatively
titled processing event
uh so synthesis and digital libido and
prosthetic trilogy together
yeah very cool very cool i think the
thread of exodology is something which
uh
brings us all together in an interesting
way it's um andrew you've written
an essay about it and alexander as you
just mentioned
it's a key theme and we've sort of
titled
maybe some sort of direction for this
conversation as
exodus from the old empire which are
kind of
fascinating as well so and it has a
double meaning of course
because none of us none of us is english
and none of us is american
so it seems we've we've exited
both uh empires in this case uh one of
us is a canadian one of us is south
africa one is in australia and we can
let the audience guess who's which right
well i left england when i was 11. so if
we're playing the national identity game
then i'd i'd still go for england in a
game of football or something like this
but um but i'm like you did your exodus
that's why
you did your accident yeah exactly yeah
you done it you left you left the old
world and you're in the new
world now yeah but we're not exactly
talking about going to new nation states
really at the end of the day
i think um after reading your books
alexander the
the depth of the change that you speak
about
and the kind of um the fundamentality of
the shift
in uh environment
that we find ourselves interacting and
living in is one which is
deeper broader than something which can
be encapsulated
by the nation state so be kind of
interesting to sort of
get a sense of in the in the from
from the big picture when when you're
talking about
exodus when you're talking about exodus
where are we now and where are we
potentially going to well okay
so human beings either operate through
genes or memes
um and the genetic is also tied to
physical territory
okay so as long as we could expand on
this planet and just conquer new
territory
regardless of who we killed in the
process we could do that
and what cerakus now are claiming is
that that whole process
reached an abrupt end in the late 1950s
so ironically 1950s we were in the
shadow of the second world war
uh we just created the atomic bomb which
meant we just realized that we could
kill ourselves in a second
uh but also the late 1950s china
conquered tibet
and the united states literally
conquered hawaii
so whenever i hear americans you know
talk about china has to get out to bed
always remind the americans
you should get out of hawaii first you
hypocrites right so we had the last
territories that were conquered in the
kind of um
a repetition of that achievement if you
consider that a successful achievement
which i think it is from an imperial
point of view certain years
china got tibet and america got hawaii
but 10 years later
you've got the moon landing and the moon
landing has
you know been axiomatically celebrated
ever since
like a great achievement that human
beings managed to set foot on the moon
if we look at it realistically if you
look at world the world economy over the
last say 50 to 100 years
we discovered that the moonlight was
probably the most terrible project human
beings have ever undertaken in terms of
just wasting money on absolutely nothing
so three guys dance around on the moon
and the cost
for each step of those guys dancing
around the moon is like hundreds of
billions of dollars
which could have you know decreased
poverty status from current climate
change and all kinds of problems you
could have avoided if you spent the
money more wisely
so apparently we stopped being wise
quite a long time ago like after 1945 we
went cuckoo
we weren't twice before that because we
created hitler and stalin and mao before
that
but certainly the response hitler
installed him out was to go completely
infantile
youth oriented sex obsessed hating
wisdom
throwing wisdom out through the door and
instead going for something incredibly
infantile
and the fact that we can't even see that
the
end of the exodus towards the new
territory
reached a definite end in the 1950s and
something
actually had started already 4 000 years
earlier which is the exodus of ideas
say you travel from one time period into
the next one you can actually create
a higher state of civilization not that
our minds get any better we usually get
more and more stupid which step we take
in history
but actually through technology and the
technological advancements
we can move from one paradigm to the
next
and this is why what certification are
doing in the very aristotelian sense
with something we call paradigmatics
paradigmatics is simply looking around
at the world you live in and especially
looking around at the world you're
moving into
and then try to define what kind of
world is that what would it pay off to
invest in
so for example now early 2020s
would it really pay off to invest in
politics well
does anyone of your friends want to be a
politician anymore no
and america has now resorted to choosing
between cartman from south park and a
corona corps for president
it's it's not like they're making an
effort to become politicians anymore
right
so politics has gone ironic academia has
gone ironic academia is dead and over
nobody wants to go
into academia any longer they're suing
the hell out of each other these days
what they're doing
and it's gone woke and all those things
and obviously all the industry is dying
too because all the industry is now
being gripped by communication agencies
that are trying to politicize even the
commercial environment
so they're all done okay that means
there's no point in investing in them
when investing in the future certainly
not putting your kids through any of
those three institutions
or have your kids aspire towards any of
them rather we have to define what we
call in our work and autocracy
like who are going to be the winners in
the digital realm
so we move into a world of digital and
augmented reality
and the question is who's going to be a
winner in that realm and the funny thing
is when we started asking these
questions 25 years ago
we were pretty alone in actually asking
those questions which is like
the ultimate cell phone book is not how
to help yourself survive a dying
paradigm
the ultimate self a book should really
be uh what would it mean to live in the
future since we know as much about the
future as we actually do
so this is what a proper paradigmatic
should do today and that's what we work
with
[ __ ] yeah beautiful thank you for that
awesome introduction
andrew as a as a musician and a writer
and um and an independent thinker who's
been following
similar threads to myself over the last
several years interested in john
pavaki's work
and jordan peterson and buddhism
and various things how do you relate to
this sort of um
this this picture that alexander's just
laid down
well i think um i'm less of a
philosopher than alexander and
i'm more uh let's say interested in the
i don't know if this is the right word
the interior aspect of the exodus
like um like the mystical aspect of the
exodus
right so so um i think
it's it's a it's a primordial myth and i
think in the judeo
christian tradition there's all these
primordial myths that we're still living
so i think if there's there's an exodus
for now like there has to there's
dead and dying world that that we have
to move beyond
and there's another world to go to and i
think alexander's work is sort of
mapping out like
you know how to do that and so i'm
interested in the spiritual aspect of
the exodus
how to do that on you know on a
spiritual level like you know what kind
of human being
we need to become right uh in order to
let's say embody this this exodus
um yeah and i should add it that in our
work we consider everything to be
religion
so it's either bad or good religion but
you cannot avoid being religious
um so yeah spirit spirituality here is
just basically any form of
you know human exercise towards a
certain goal or or
a certain achievement you're setting out
so that's what we agree
i would say that if you do exodus
so you're doing the studies of
successful and not so successful
migrations throughout history
these are both migrations in physical
space and migrations in terms of ideas
okay so if you do exodus properly you
try to find patterns
on what was successful and why it worked
and to see if it could work again
or not so you try to learn from these
that's exactly when we go back to things
like the exodus out of egypt the exodus
out of babylon
and the exodus from europe to israel the
three major jewish exodus for example
they're also exodus of ideas for example
that we originally lived in a
nomadic tribal religion which we call
nomidology it's last trend in today
would be say hinduism
which means it's a religion of the
eternal return of the same
where no improvement is ever possible
hopefully you avoid things getting worse
but with evantology with the idea that
actually
the sun has access to more information
than the father did because it's a very
masculine trait but like
say the son has access to more
information the father did which is
according to marshall mcluhan the
revolution of written language
once you could write things down which
started about say 8
000 years ago and then increased over
time
you could store information outside of
your own brain and we could do that the
sun could then suddenly realize i could
actually potentially create a better
world than my dad could possibly do
simply because i have access to more
information this is the foundation of
technology
and therefore the foundation of
civilization in my case i even converted
to the religion that invented this idea
which is zoroastrianism
and so rasterism when i did that in the
1980s i did my studies of eastern
philosophy i
of course i studied all the major hindu
and buddhist traditions and
that's something with all three an
interest to all three share
i started taoism and chinese and
japanese philosophy but when i finally
converted i picked the old
persian philosophical tradition because
i was even more interested that at the
time and then it turns
out that today this is a very important
bridge between east and west because the
only thing that connects eastern
religion historically
with western metaphysics starting with
abrahamic religions and eventually going
on to the greeks and european philosophy
and all that
the western tradition what is west of
the gobi desert so to speak it was east
of the gobi desert the only thing that
connects the two is actually the persian
tradition
so guys like me who actually have
studied this for the past 30 years
becoming
really important right now to try to
connect chinese indian
european middle eastern thinking but
that wasn't the purpose when i converted
i converted because i love the idea that
zoroaster
as hegel anitra points out so raster is
the only really radical new thinker in
history
in the sense that he was the only one
who broke with nominology
he broke with the idea that everything
must always return to the same and said
no wait a second
it could potentially be different with
each repetition of the same
there's a slight difference and if that
difference is harvested and nurtured
through increased knowledge which is the
name of with
of which the name is technology then
with technology we can create a
civilization
so i'm totally i'm a civilizationist i'm
really interested in
what has made civilization work in the
past
and we look at that question what's
interesting then are the exodus
because what happens is that you've got
a lot of dramatic
uh new things happening around you like
right now we're living in a paradigm
shift where like the entire world has
been thrown
online due to the corona pandemic and
something we've prepared for being
confused about
an environment that's full of children's
diseases like facebook and instagram
they're obviously not working as
intended
because we're making all the mistakes
you do when you apply the rules of an
old paradigm onto a new paradigm
you simply have the wrong paradigmatics
when we see all this happening right now
2020 it's obvious we've been thrown into
a new world and the new power is going
to be online
the tech giants have gone through the
roof from the stock markets
amazon google facebook and our empires
they need to be questioned need them
broken up
we have to start fighting them because
they're so damn powerful
now this was all bound to happen during
tournament because we haven't learned
from history that this is what happens
at a paradigm shift
then the question is so who would then
go first
this is why i always tell people that i
i have to be a nietzschem
but i expect my students to be more
marxist
what i mean with that is that nietzsche
proposes the uberman she proposes
somebody who steps forward and goes
ahead
and walks into the new territory and
thereby becomes an example others can
copy and the question then for my
students is
if i work very hard on defining the
nietzsche and ubermensch in the digital
realm today who goes
first who becomes the nettocrat then
it's your damn job to make sure as many
people as possible can become netocrats
but this is where the hard stuff comes
in we cannot learn from the previous
paradigm
because the previous paradigm due to its
exploitative approach
towards the world towards human beings
was built on the naive
assumption that we could all have access
to all information at all times and
handle it
and this is called the barred absolute
not my name barb but b-a-r-r-e-d like
you you religion you need a bar you need
a wall that says you cannot go beyond
this wall because you're not prepared
for it yet
in eastern thinking this is different
between sutra and tantra
it exists as a raster religion the jews
adamant about it but islamic
christianity was swept away because
these pop religions
wanted everybody to have access to god
at all times
and we inherited that in western society
we inherited this tradition that
oh everything is available to everybody
at all times
and now parents are coming along to
philosophers like me and said
my god my five-year-old is watching
violent pornography online what am i
gonna do
well you gotta go back and look at the
last two thousand years of history
you had a religion that tore down the
curtain in the temple and they said
god should be available to everybody at
all times meaning that truth should be
available to all people at all times
we cannot handle truth unless we're
prepared for it
and this is why we work so much now with
the different stages in your life what
you can handle when you're a teenager
which you can handle when you're 25
which you can handle with your 45
which you can handle when you're 65 and
possibly one day you could be an
elder in your community because you've
lived life to its fullest and you're
ready to give back
and this is what these western cultures
have always been about this is why
jordan peterson
john f varkey these cognitive scientists
these art historians are back in vogue
and while people are listening to them
because people are really asking if we
don't get the western right this time
before we enter digital we're gonna
violent poor
throne at babies or three months old
so this is what our work is about this
is where
my work with certificates ties in with
the work of peterson and for vacation
why they're all friends
now you get the bigger thing yeah yeah
yeah can i can i just
ask one question before you interject uh
about about
you know about this this netocratic
elite right
okay this is i think the thing that
people have the hardest time
uh with is is is that is the idea of the
elite and the idea of a j of authority
right somebody
has has more authority than somebody
else in this egalitarian childish sort
of
milieu so i i think that the the hard
thing for people to hear
is is that there's a there's an elite
right
and there's also an authority i've been
thinking about this and i was thinking
i'm thinking about how do you say that
without
sounding like an [ __ ] like because no
sound like an
audition the traditions that i work in
you you don't just
walk right in the door and and have
everything offered to you
there's there's stages before you get
there and there's work and there's study
and there's development and
that no way to say wait a second andrew
i am not here to put on some gloves and
give people the hard news in a soft way
because we don't have the time for that
we don't have the time for that when
things start happening as quickly as
they're happening now we got peterson
from arcadis guy site that warned us at
least in america and europe for the last
few years
okay things are happening this is a
rapid piece we don't have time to put on
gloves and say nice things any longer i
think
go back to the original mythologist
exactly like peterson says
go back to the store the exodus out of
egypt people
the egyptians were warned again and
again and again and
finally you had to paint something on
your door because the angel death
walked by and killed the oldest son in
the family
because he was so angry with the old
society this is all symbolic but it's
the
anger with an old paradigm that is so
corrupt and decadent that it just
refuses to move its ass
the elite here were the hebrews the
hebrews were clearly as sigmund point
pointed out an
egyptian sect who knew that they had to
move into monotheistic paradigm
they had failed miserably with atonism
during it not untitan common that failed
and tutankhamun had become their christ
it was killed by the priest
there was an athens sect in egypt that
were a minority
but they were sharp as hell and they
were smart and they took to the new
technology they took to the new paradigm
they understood what was required in the
next phase of history
and they declared that it was called
atonism and later become judaism
so this cult had to leave egypt and they
were also they're also slaves
which is interesting because that's
exactly what an elite are the elite
is always the slaves of the last
paradigm who studied deep
worked hard and don't get rewarded for
it this is the exact parallel to karl
marx
proletariat you've got to remember that
marx is jewish
marx gets this so marx and freud these
guys coming out of the hegelian
revolution in europe
they're really understanding history
fully and i think
freud was on to this in his last work
before he died moses is monotheism an
excellent book to study this deeper
we're digging deep into to now fully
understand the best judaism
and heritage we get from the jews right
but the hebrews left egypt they were an
elite
they were the original proletariat who
walked
out on the old into the new because they
couldn't
make in the old what they wanted to
achieve in the new
but then by bringing that faith out
into the open more people can be
recruited and join the faith
later in the new promised land and we
can just we can just move that into the
world of ideas and then it's
instead of discussing which territory
we're going to do this thing because all
you need to be digital these days is to
have a city state like
in europe estonia slovenia and isil are
preparing for this revolution you
already got dubai and singapore
you don't need huge territories like
united states you don't need a huge
territory like communist china
to actually be part of the new
revolution because it's all about
putting a data center somewhere that
data says more powerful than all the
territory you could ever conquer
so it's not about physical territory
this time that's the whole point
this is a vertical exodus not a
horizontal one
it's a vertical exodus it's an exodus
into the world of ideas into super ideas
into depth yeah depth which we call the
root of the phallus
so that we can be phallic and direct the
phallus upward
so the root of the phallus is to learn
from history more than ever
study history deeper than ever use data
to get into the the the original known
methodology the original society getting
to get into human beings come from
understand better what it means to be
human like like like if the machine is
gonna ask us in 20 years time
who are you and the philosophical
question you can ask
what does it mean to be human we have to
answer that question again
but deeper at this time to be able to
shoot higher aim higher
that's the exodus we're doing now and
that's the exodus we're preparing for
so this exodus is an exodus into the
digital realm for sure and the question
is
we're seeing the first of the three
metocrys already those are the tech
giants we predicted this 25 years ago
first you got the informationalists
the guys who pick the data and process
the data
second we're going to have the
sensocrats we're going to live in police
states
that's for sure we're gonna have cameras
and microphones that we're
observing everything we do whenever
somebody tells me these days well i
turned off my computer yesterday i
walked out of the park and i'm just like
and you think you went offline have you
ever heard of satellites
have you ever heard of microphones
they're everywhere now so the question
is
what kind of police states can we have
how can we still be free and liberal
within those police states and creative
because the problem with dictatorship is
not a moral one the problem dictatorship
is that it stops being creative
so those questions need to be answered
that's where we should be now in our
thinking as we move forward
and this is why we have to go back to
the previous access and
listen telling people that we need a new
elite that it's already being
established
that's just mincemeat here but obviously
we have a new elite coming out of
silicon valley and they're all
billionaires
and some of them think better than
others peter thiel think better than
elbow musk for sure you know but
at least they're doing what they set out
to do they're informationalist
then come the sensocrats who will
replace the current politicians
why would you vote every four years when
you vote every second
how could you how could you anyway
defend a vote every four years for
corona corps
or cartman in south park when you
literally vote every second better than
you vote every four years
okay then after the censorcrafts come
possibly and hopefully the protopians
protopin great word by kevin kelley he
found it he should credit for it
but originally the idea for tokens comes
from the persons called fraschuk
to live in the forever refreshing
protopia of ever change
it's not a utopian it's not utopian this
token it is an ideal
state to live in where you create it's
not a final enlightenment
it's uh it's a it's a it's a um you know
it's a creative constantly renewing
itself
you know yeah it can be a philosophical
absolute but it's certainly not a
creative absolute in any way whatsoever
proctop is a statement philosophy might
reach an end yes
what it means to be human might reach an
end yes we might leave it to the
machines to you know conquer outer space
so we stay on the planet which we should
okay so we might reach an end human
history in a way philosophically
speaking but
certainly not creatively i mean i i
would say that this could be an artistic
golden age more than anything and we
call it protopia
protopians is what we call these people
so now you've got the three new elites
and you see how the old industry is
being replaced by informationalist
data replaces capital you see how
sensocracy is replacing politics
because that's the imaginary power and
you've got a new narrative being
dictated by a new symbolic power
the the way the academia replaced the
church is the way that academia will be
replaced by the protopians
and this sort of is the beginning what
we're doing kind of right now is sort of
we're starting a new narrative
like like this is the the shadowy realm
where the like i think kegel says that
where the new narrative starts to bubble
up
tim i think i interrupted you last time
i
in your last question we are literally
the hebrews in egypt
preparing for the exodus and the last
warning is about to be signed on the
doors yes
yes
well that is some beginning
beautiful job that's how about you tim
how about you tim our followers want to
know you better
why is the gorgeous young man sitting in
the circle and showing off his hairy
chest
oh yeah um how to integrate that with
this last 20 minutes of um
of uh philosophical thought and see if
we can weave the hairy chest in there
towards the end
poor man so i
so just to describe my my state with
this it's like
there's so there's so much vision here
that i resonate with
strongly and then there's a kind of
feeling into it which wants to depart
from all these different places
and it's kind of like um it's like there
are these different
parts that i want to sort of look at and
go hmm okay how does this connect to
this
or my perspective on this is with this
vocabulary
but then i'm worried about going down
one particular route
might not necessarily speak to the whole
in a way that
does actual justice to the resonance
which that i share
for the vision and the whole as
presented so my first point would
actually be
sort of a meta point about the nature of
interaction itself and the actual degree
of time that's required
to really sit with in a relational
process
these themes these concepts these
feelings and
uh from the grandiosity up actually to
the kind of
i don't know if i can use the lateral
but at the any rate the kind of
embodied sort of breathing it through
process
so i'm someone who's interested in both
of these things hey i'm interested in
the dynamics of
of artful interaction
and i'm also interested in a clarity of
vision and how these kinds of things
interact
so as far as what i'm doing and what i'm
interested in
it's something like okay how as as one
of the things
how can we get together as an expanding
but
an appropriately slowly expanding
network of interaction
so as to involve as much of the
human psyche as possible so as to share
in the fullness of perception as
possible
and use something like a use processes
of discernment
to together collectively sharing a
vision
that can attend to what's fundamentally
worth caring about
as well as it can attend to the clarity
and
integrity as far as analysis is
concerned
so in this sense an interest in both
analysis and mysticism or the kind of
the inside out
feeling of what it is to be in
relationship as well as the kind of um
clarity and metaphysical
um integrity of
what we're talking about so where that
takes this discussion i'm not sure
but that's how i come at these things
from a broad
sort of life project perspective well
that's great i mean
andrew and i especially when we do our
our webcast together with thomas hamrick
who's also
a you know tantric teacher is that
there's great vocabulary from the east
that's not so common in the west so we
can start using it
and you can then apply it later on
christianity and post christianity in
the west too there's no problem at all
but you're talking i think on the
individuals i prefer to say the
individual level
you're talking about meditation and and
and contemplation practices
and the great thing is that all the silk
group traditions in the east
uh were adamant that this was really
really important you spent most your
time
when you were being religious actually
meditating or contemplating
and we know these terms already in india
it's called the diana it's often
referred to as yoga practices in the
west this is called the dayena
in iran personal practices and daina
actually if you look at the word itself
from sagdon to china becomes chan
when it comes to china and then becomes
tien in vietnam
becomes zeon in korea it becomes zen
in japan so they said this is thread all
over the east from zen in japan
all the way down to the diana in
in india and so we have all of these
traditions a meditation and
contemplation practices and
the way it worked along the silk road is
that you walked into new oasis and you
were a traitor and
and you you might go to the whorehouse
if you were lucky you went certainly to
a hospice somewhere and had a meal and
you stayed overnight you know in the
guest house and and
and you went to the bath house to get
cleaned because you had camel hair and
dust all over you
but you most of all went to what's
called the kostok
and the kostag is the origin we today
called monasteries
the cloisters and the modernities of the
west actually originated in asia
and i think kostok is a beautiful sort
of neutral term today
for a place where you go to meditate
contemplate and reflect right i would
add
you also study because there's no point
in just sitting there
trying to find some kind of empty
consciousness and then contemplating
what am i going to spend the day
doing how am i going to be a
constructive spirit rather destructive
spirit today
that's what i do in my two xiaomi the
practices every morning
but on the individual level if you start
before we start interacting one another
i think it's really important to stress
that it's absolutely pointless in
speaking about paradigmatics
and speaking about spiritual practices
so speaking about how we're going to
enter the digital
augmented realm keeping our humanity and
our spirituality intact
unless we go back to and learn these
practices
how's that for a start yeah yeah can i
say what i got from what you what you
were saying um
the first thing that came to my mind is
that is that you know uh
this is it's a communal enterprise in
some sort but where where
you develop friendship over time and
that that
that you know that makes the ideas
uh that that um that's the creative
process right
uh which is something to do with
friendship that was my first thought
um and i also was thinking about what
i've been exploring recently in in terms
of my own practice
and uh normally i'm a vajrayana buddhist
but i've been looking into jewish
esotericism
what you do is you look at uh you know
in this practice that i'm i'm exploring
you look at an image
right and then you allow the mental you
know
associations and you allow the intellect
to work on that image and to explore
that image you know it might be an
alchemical image that has sulfur and
mercury and the sun and the moon and you
know all these kind of
primordial things and you you work on
that image
intellectually and you you you look at
it as if you were looking at a
you know you know an icon or something
like that and you you
you go deep into that and that's the
intellectual aspect and you do that for
20 minutes and the next part
is is you try to hold the image in your
mind
in silence and that becomes a whole
different level of experience
and then the third level you just drop
the whole thing and you have this
and you allow it to kind of become a
free play a free creative play
of a an exploration
so you have to go through these these
stages where first you look at the image
you know and you have the intellectual
stage and then and then
where it becomes embodied right right
you know it becomes not theoretical
right uh and then and then and then
and then there's another stage of
freedom which is is
is just pure exploration
and here's here's one of the good news
philosophically speaking is that
uh after immortal [ __ ] the west broke we
do a listen
when you use the term embodied here
andrew that's very very important
we actually have today a worldview where
we are embodied
so we assume the body and mind the two
aspects of the same thing
and this is of course the dominant
tradition of the east
but we actually inherited in the west we
did that philosophically before
even we started like schopenhauer
started going to asia and took buddha
with him back
and you know hegel anita took to roster
with them back and all that
but but actually even before that we had
that break i think the break between
kant and hegel in western philosophy in
the early 1800s
is to break with dualism towards modesto
and of course binosa
was the pioneer of that long before
hegel who also was a modest he was a
modest as opposed to cartesian dualism
but we already left the idea that we can
be human beings and separate
uh the body from the mind and in all
work i see today all spiritual work i
see today
this this embodied experience is
absolutely central
so this is great because actually that
means that
a lot of the western tradition that
would have been very problematic today
is no longer problematic
it's already out the window i mean it's
even christianity is trying to find some
modest roots today and
hopefully to go back to the neoplatons
to try to find that
but but we are already living in
accordance with an
understanding of that we live in a
modest universe and that we are modest
human beings within that universe
so these yeah practices must be embodied
absolutely it makes no sense otherwise
and actually we know from history that
people who try to separate body and mind
and walk out into the forest so raster
warned us about this
any guy who walks out into the forest
and thinks his mind is separated from
his body
we call the pillars afterwards those are
the guys that always cause havoc and
history
the people who are not embodied can have
the brightest smartest ideas but when
you look
closer at those ideas they come from
people who deny
their own bodies to deny their own
sexuality for example
and those people are always the most
dangerous i think a lot of the stuff
that's come out of silicon valley so far
has been of that nature
i call it gnostic dualism right gnostic
yes silicon valley is about escaping the
body in some sense into some
kind of uh you know machine
yeah that uploading thing like if you
were uploaded into a machine and you no
longer had access to your body that
would be the most
horrible thing ever that means the
thought hasn't even been thought through
but
the people who you promote uploading
it's it's
we got to get that navy out the door
quickly so we we're really attacking an
internet that is just full of children's
diseases it's
right now it's it's infantile it's hyper
narcissistic
it's fostering all the worst things in
people but it's not to regulating the
internet you're gonna get it right
because the people are supposed to
regulate the internet
who are they well they're woke people
and they're platonist
engineers and all kinds of where people
don't make it even worse
right now i don't think we can regulate
the internet in any constructive
meaningful way because the people who
are trying to do it
have not done their paradigmatics
properly first
and in that case it's better to leave it
anarchy and let people learn through
their own mistakes
but rather try to politically or
commercially
dictate what people should consume and
see when they go online
because that's gonna that's gonna be
even worse than what we have today
that's what i'm adamant about right now
better to stay with the anarchy and try
to learn as quickly as possible from the
mistakes we're making so we're having
platonists
who created cynical platforms like
facebook which is all about owning your
eyes and
you know putting advertisement into your
system without even knowing about it
like the most sinister thing you could
ever do like you you don't like spam
we're gonna
force feed you spam that's facebook
okay we have discovered that on a
massive scale already
people are healthily now preferring to
take a walk in the park rather to stay
in those environments
but we got to go back and see we can do
with the internet but i think
leading by creative example is a much
better way than censorship right now
because i'm terrified
if politics just move online right now
and try to censor what we consume alike
because then we're going to get no
better than communist china
then the west is going to be exactly
common as china it's going to be
terrible
yeah there are some movements in
australia to do just this thing i
haven't looked into it much so i can't
speak to it too much
but you know somewhat ironically there
was um google and
facebook letting me know that hey
there's a danger there's a danger to
your uh
freedom of choice on the internet here
and it's coming in the form of
the australian government wanting to
sort of um up regulate
certain media sources that are legacy
media sources in australia
over potential alternative kind of
sources and i think there's some sort of
guys that
coronavirus and misinformation and that
whole dynamic is being used to sort of
try and get this in i haven't followed
it but it's interesting
oh yeah and they're using the corona
pandemic asset excuse which is really
when you should watch out
right so we have to understand that
these old institutions are falling apart
and why they're now also victims to woke
ideology or soda ideology simply because
nobody with the right minds are there
any longer
but we still have politics so we still
have academia we still have old industry
around and all this just forcing us to
buy their products and
and academia is forcing us to believe
that [ __ ] they put out
although nobody's listening any longer
and who reads an academic paper for
god's sake right
and politics is like bunch of losers
left
but they all try to regain power
by pointing out and moralizing against
the online world today as if the world
they represent
would be any better every time students
come up to me here in scandinavia and
ask me about fake news
i remind them that the printing press
produced only but
nothing but fake news but it was fake
news according
to the power that ruled that society and
actually what they call fake news online
is often something that questions that
power
bad or good up to you to decide for
yourself
just get yourself five different news
sources just like the only way we can
fight dictatorship eventually is by
being able to give our data to five
different sources
and five different agents rather than to
just one
i think that ultimately at the end of
the day that's going to be the models we
have to start creating so
but i think censoring the internet right
now i'm totally against it and and i
don't mean this is a classic libertarian
i mean this as a marxist i mean this is
a nietzschean i mean this is a hegelian
i mean this is a historian
it's just because if you're gonna have
censorship then who are who are going to
be the censors when
it's going to be the very people who
come from the old paradigm and
understand the new power down the worst
and try to prevent the new novel from
happening
that'd be like the worst thing ever so
right now we've got to live with the
anarchy for
for quite a while yet
[Music]
yeah so there are a couple threads which
i think might take me about eight hours
to actually stitch together so you're
gonna have to help out
um because i i want to
it would be really beautiful to
introduce the
um distinction and development in the
history of ideas
from relativism to a sort of
relationalism that you speak about
in synthesism this is something that um
i have a lot of appreciation for
and i think is resonant among many of
the philosophers
that are circling this kind of
discussion
um and i i wonder if we could tie that
also to the following things
um because i know you're involved in
men's work and i know you
um appreciate the importance of
mentorship and the kind of
well obviously wisdom traditions and how
we can extend the hand
at all developmental levels to become
what we can be so as to properly take
responsibility
and act in a mature way in a way that
can respond to the dynamics of our times
in
relationship with each other and then
also also there's a thread in
some of your thinking and it's part of
this notion of exodus as well
right that there's a certain movement
away from
um a large block let's say a large block
of people
to me there is there i wouldn't say
inconsistency but there's a bit of work
at least in my mind to sort of
weave these things together because um
this the idea that there can be a hard
cut
place between who can or cannot
participate is something
that well either we should be wary of or
take great care
in making i mean we do have to exclude
right there there comes a point where
conflict is unavoidable i'm not making a
case that
some sort of radical inclusion is what
i'm interested in here
however from a from a
i'm sort of from a perspective from a
perspective that is most resonant with
me
it's like there's
there's a when i look at human beings
when i look at the vast majority of
human beings and i
i really sit with them i see and i feel
a longing for a kind of
connection and um place
in the world that i see as something
which i inherently
i care for that thing i i feel it in a
way that i want to
support it and i want to be in right
relationship
with it but i want to do so in a way
that's sustainable
and not energetically destructive of my
own
immediate domain of necessary um
what uh stability um homeostasis or wha
or what have you right so so there's
this interesting phenomenon
where as far as i can tell their hand
should be extended
maximally for integris interaction
and yet at the same hand on the same on
the other hand we are speaking about
something which is a
a movement away from
a kind of previous paradigmatic attitude
which is not
fit to actually be sustainable in the
world as it is currently developing
so how is that as a sort of frame is
that something that's popping up for you
as like uh
what can we say about this i think we
well i'm writing a lot about you know
both andrew and i are involved immense
work here in europe we should say that
uh
but uh we talk about the term
adultification
so if jordan peterson for example and
john privacy and i share something in
common it's that we want to adult defy
the world
when we were the dultifications that
adultification was absolutely essential
in the original tribal environment
at certain ages you were expected to do
certain things otherwise you wouldn't
get your reward
and the ultimate reward would be right
to passage and even after the rite of
passage you would have to go through
a period as a young adult before you
were actually fully accepted as an adult
so the adultification process being
destroyed by the society we lived in
and it's been destroyed because we human
beings are born with
being given absolutely everything and
that's sucking the tit
and that's the way it should work okay
the mamilla we call it the miller rather
than the tip
the mamilla is there as soon as
important we get out of the matrix which
is like
nine months of absolute paradise
everything is given to you you don't
even have to think
there's no sense of self in the matrix
in the womb because you have to think
you don't have to solve problems uh
and actually that's not even the case
when you instinctively crawl your way up
to the tit and start sucking the tick
but the mamilla and the magic of all the
breast milk you get when you suck it
like it comes from out of nowhere
okay that is the original fantasy we
live in
and that fountain system tore apart and
the problem is
our society does not encourage children
to love how these things are torn apart
for them how these fantasies are
destroyed and how the new
even tougher even more brutal reality is
opening up behind each curtain that you
tear down
the first one of those is called the
phallic intrusion it should happen when
you're one year old
and it's simply called phallic intrusion
because the phallus is what what
intrudes into your relationship to the
mamilla and your
childhood is then the relationship
between the manila that supports you and
provides for you at all times
and you're playing a grown-up that's
what being a child is playing rob
while you're striving towards the
phallic state which is to be a proper
grown-up and you want to be grown up so
bad
and a healthy child wants to be grown up
so bad and one day you get to that point
your biology first kicks in
hey your genital organs grow and they
start functioning in a dramatic new way
you never thought would happen right
and then you are actually prepared
through your studies and through your
playing as a child to become an adult
now we have to understand that this
process is broken down
so i'm often talking to 25 year olds
who who sound like 12 year olds when
they talk and the first thing i do is i
don't blame them for them i try to give
them a bigger picture and explain
that we have postponed adulthood in our
society this again how we
youth over wisdom we prioritize
childhood over adulthood
we postponed adulthood pushed it further
into our lives
later to be encountered later and this
fights and struggles enormously with our
biology
and that's how we have so many problems
young girls with eating disorders and
and and kids come in teenagers come in
and they can't understand how the
sexuality actually operates
and the obsession with consent culture
which is completely understandable
because
the guys don't even know when the
consent happens any longer to the girls
because they're not mature enough to
understand the signaling
so many of the cultural problems have
today are simply a problems
of that the adultification process
doesn't happen when actually we're
obliged to make it happen
we cannot fight our own biology at a
certain age you need to be this
amount of adult to be able to handle
life now
once you've been able to handle adult
life you also know that not everybody
can go to dinner party
the host decides she gets to go to the
dinner party
not everybody everybody gets to sleep
with a beautiful girl in the bar
actually maybe only one guy gets to
sleep with her
not even him you'll be turned down
you get nose these are the barred
absolutes we have in our life already
and to be really honest about it here
we're sitting right now in australia
and france and sweden with our
microphones on
with our digital equipment and we're
wealthy guys in wealthy countries
the vast majority of people on this
planet are poor and they live in poor
countries and we have borders
that will not permit them to come and
visit us when we're located
these are again borrowed absolutes so
our lives are full of these barred
absolutes and and the
the sooner way to teach the kids that
i'm sorry you're not gonna get
everything in your life
and by the way somebody had to support
your mother when she gave you that
breast milk
so she could give it to you it didn't
just mystically magically come out of
nowhere
somebody put in some really hard work
for her to be able to breastfeed you
and for kids to understand ah there's
cost and effect
and there are these beautiful processes
and once they understand that they can
become truly adult and
only then can they have adult relations
with other adults which is a real
adulthood
it is not about you it's about the
relations that you pursue and get
involved and interact with
as an adult so you one day can become a
parent
and have a child again another
relationship
we can't do these relationships properly
unless we get this right first and i
think that's why the call for the
adultification of society is so strong
can i respond uh tim to to what you said
we were saying
of course i agree with all that and uh
and um
that adultification you know uh
um the question of being an adult what
occurs to me is is you you are in
service
you know to the world which i think is
what you're longing for and you're
in the in your question is to be of
service to the world that's something to
do with being an adult
in the buddhist tradition they call that
the bodhisattva or something right it's
not about you anymore it's about
uh serving the world right um so you you
grow out of your adolescent
self-concerned and
you know you know 20 20 something people
are often
they're very concerned especially today
where there's this
self-obsession the self-contraction the
self-concern where you're not open to
the world
so i i think that that the altruistic
thing is is yes you're open to the world
and helping people you know in
in in a radical sense but at the same
time you're
you're brokenhearted because you're like
neo walking through the matrix
and you see all these people and there's
no hope for them in some sense right uh
and there's nothing you can do about it
and they're not your friends uh you know
um uh um unless unless
what you need to do is find the right
people to be around who encourage you
and lift you up and and then
in that way you you you might help those
people you know who are
completely um imprisoned uh in the
matrix imprisoned in this mechanical
you know uh you know uh who are kind of
stuck
in in um um you know just
mechanical thinking and don't have any
freedom whatsoever
yeah various kind of um reciprocal
closing patterns of of addiction
is something i'm hearing to say i mean
it's it's something that um obviously
jumper vacay speaks about quite a bit
but you know addiction does characterize
so much of
of modern life and of course but it's an
addiction that is so
uh hidden that you don't even know it's
an addiction it's just your life right
well it doesn't it doesn't addiction
problem and i agree with tim it's
massive right now doesn't addiction
problem
precisely come in into history when we
stop believing the future
and especially for young men okay i i
work i support some women with women's
work but i work mostly with young men
i did not study psychiatry but i love it
and i work with psychiatrists and i'm a
psychoanalyst and
okay the time i get off when i don't you
know enjoy myself having conversations
with you guys and reading books and
writing books okay
which is what i love i try to help guys
out that have these disorders right now
and addiction is
is always all over the place and i just
try to teach them listen
there might not be peter pan syndrome
here the problem might not be that
you're
too much of a child still and that
you're too
immature yet still and you're too
narcissistic although you're 25 and that
was okay when you were 15 but it's not
okay any longer
you should have found your purpose you
should have found meaning in your life
by the time you're at right now when
you're 25
but what happens is that when you don't
believe in the future and that could be
for very healthy reasons that could be
because nobody talks about the future in
the society where you live
and everybody stop believing in it that
means a friend of mine peter towson
who's a friend of
uh andrew stewart he's like he's like a
savant he came up with the term he said
wait a second you guys have worked with
the peter pan syndrome all the time
why don't you work on the opposite what
do you mean why don't you work with the
fact that young man can be incredibly
healthy
well prepared for life but he lives in a
really deranged age
where nobody talks about the future at
all and as soon as you don't talk about
the future
your mind will go depressed because your
mind will circulate back and go back
eternally go back to everything you've
done in your life and you will blame
yourself
for all the shortcomings you had because
you got there's no meaning to anything
you went through because it doesn't lead
forward to anything else and this lack
of purpose of meaning is incredibly
painful
and we call it the calligula syndrome
because we all think of collegal of the
roman empire as an evil guy because we
were always taught it's called the
colleague
that was really evil he burned our room
and killed people all the time but a
collegial action was probably a very
healthy young man
who grew up with a really nasty uncle
tiberius
and was brought up by him and then
basically one day tiberius walked into
the room and told caligula
you're now the roman emperor you're now
uh the king of the world
you know what everybody hates you wants
to kill you what are you gonna do next
well you would be paranoid wouldn't you
right and the paranoia that caligula
must have experienced at that time
is precisely the paranoia you get when
there is no future
so depression means you go back and just
rehearse
everything you're going through and as a
man at least women blame it on everybody
else and
it's called borderline diagnosis men
blame it on themselves and that's called
male depression and we're seeing a
pandemic of this depression right now
depression and bipolarity is everywhere
young men and i try to teach them it's
not your fault
this is because we stopped believing in
the future
so because we don't have an but we don't
have an exodus myth
that that's the problem right which
comes back to
we don't have this exodus myth which is
means that you can break out of your
present situation then
there will be something uh there will be
a promised land
and it's not about you being part of the
cool gang who do the exodus not at all
all you need to do young men is tell
them
of the exodus tell them digital will
create an
endless opportunity for humanity to show
themselves creatively in a way we've
never seen before
the collaboration between man and
machine we have no idea how fantastic
that could be
if we get this right so you can give
them this sort of protopin hope
and that's what we don't the protopin
hope is what you need to give young men
for example to get them out of these
depressions
and the addictions that come with it
otherwise you would just treat addiction
how you treat that
you put medication into their systems
and you have to
but you actually do it just to calm them
down and keep them alive to be honest
about it to
then foster them to present them with
the protopin hope that they can be a
part of
it's that's what great moments have done
throughout history
yeah i mean so i mean it seems to me
pretty clear this is a very trivial
statement
but vision the phallic vision
the um the absence of masculinity in a
specific sense is something you speak
about quite a lot and i think it's um
i think it's i think it's critical to
discuss i think it's very interesting
my sense is that it's bi-directional
this um uh what we
what we seek or or what we can
realize in consciousness as the sort of
stimulus
to um counteract
or or veer off the reciprocally closing
depressive addictive kind of cycle one
that's only
faced on i mean you're articulating as
something that's only looking backwards
and just recursively going over its own
experience and it's just cut off from
the world and other people in some
fundamental sense
my sense is that the um the
looking backwards i like thinking in
terms of the metaphor of an
ember and an echo i don't
really know how i can technically build
that out in a way that's fitting for
this conversation but there's a sense
from my own personal experience as
someone who
has certainly grappled with depression
for a long time
and it's pretty easily traceable in my
own life because of
my parents divorce and moving from
england to australia moving from a
certain
place of connectedness and an excellent
education to essentially somewhere rural
with um with with a school that was
not so great and and all together very
different experience i ended up not
doing lots of my final exams and
you know like went a different sort of
path um
so there was that there was that
disconnection there but there was
something which
um tuning into like
there was a basis of care that i had as
a child which not everybody has and i
appreciate that but if we even
go um psychodynamic or depth
psychological and consider the
the womb state as being that state where
there is that potential kind of
oceanic boundlessness it's often spoken
about as in stanislav
graf of course develops yeah it develops
this work very interestingly in his
observations from
lsd research in the 50s and 60s
super super interesting although of
course even in those cases
um if the pregnant mother is not having
a great time and it's not a good
pregnancy you can have complications
there and he speaks about unearthing the
kind of experiences of actual
his perinatal matrices or the stages in
the birthing process going wrong in some
fundamental sense so
there's a there's a horrible sense in
which um maybe even not all human beings
have
a kind of an unadulterated sense of
connection that is
that we can really tune into although
i'd say even in that case there's
something there's work to be done and it
can be realized
but there is something beautiful about
that about that connection and if we're
speaking about modelism
now of course we're speaking about
process and event i appreciate that
there's novelty right and uh
following whitehead and what have you
but i love that you work this into your
metaphysics
but there is this phenomenon that we are
in fact we can
it's you know might be equivocational to
speak in this way we are all connected
man
in some fundamental sense now the
mystical element of this that we can
return that we can remember and realize
these kind of states of connection
this is something distinct in in a way
from
the forward-facing vision but also
deeply informs
the dynamics or some of them at least
that we want i think want to see
present in a forward-facing vision not a
final utopia
but that but that there's something
worth caring about at all
because when i hear you know being in
relationship with machines and robots
it's like
it could be cool but why do i care about
it it's like
what like what do we care about and i
think that's it's a bi-directional thing
i just wonder what you think about that
i just want to say well i think that
alexander starts because he'll probably
say more than me
we were talking about the dark
renaissance today uh
on the chat and so we have the exodus
myth in the front
and let's say the dark renaissance
perhaps you know that's
you know it's renaissance rebirthing and
all and all that sort of stuff
myth comes so i would say like also that
the zen
arrow goes both ways so you have the
exodus going this way and then you have
the renaissance going
that way that's just something to throw
in the mix before alexander
oh yeah yeah because when we talk about
depression you recycle your own life
and it becomes uh an inverted narcissism
you never asked for the tragedy of
sitting with a depressed guy
is that he's narcissistic and he that's
the last thing he wants to be but he
can't think of anything else but blaming
himself in the process
he's not going deep enough though
because he's only going to his own
history
and when we talk about deepest or the
root of the phallus it's the history of
all mankind
this is a history of at least the last
200 000 years and hopefully even deeper
than that
and try to understand where do we come
from as a human species
and where do i fit into that so
that that's what i i would say the
tragedy we have ahead of us or the
problem to saul we have ahead of us is
that
we can definitely define that as long as
we are loyal to a clan
or tribe we can find purpose and meaning
within that clan or that tribe
because we've always done that
historically but what the jews
set out to do when they created the
jewish nation which was the first nation
in history
was that this was actually the exodus
out of egypt it was the origin of
nationalism and nationalism as
a religion they should be one of the
same thing and that's what jews practice
and hegel built on he wrote his books in
the in
in the late 19th century he used the
jewish nation as the perfect example of
the perfect national nationhood
but nationalism was an attempt at
stretching the imagination to at least
those who speak
like you or at least share your beliefs
so it's a larger population than just
merely clan or tribe
and of course before that we have all
the major stories this is the foundation
of religion
the major stories that we have two
rivers here and they share a river
system either they go to war with each
other all the time
or we have stories like cain and abel
that wonder what's going to happen if
the two river systems don't see a shared
common fate together the shared future
together
and and that's where religion
essentially is you got the hill up there
we share that hill we come from there
and we go
towards that goal which is like the
river banks of the delta that we also
share
and the rivers are separated in between
and that's where we build the temple
as i build a temple to unify the two
cultures the unification of the two
cultures
this is what civilization has tried to
do so hard for the past 5 000 years
and if you can be part of that to give
your purpose and meaning in all your
life i would say there's an almost
timeless quality to trying to create the
narrative to unify people today
we call these philosophies
cosmopolitanism
that is actually if there is no outside
there is no other
when all human beings are part of the
same tribe okay
that's hard because usually we have
another tribe
that we're opposed to and that what
gives us identity but it's a cheap route
to identity we use for 5000 years we
can't afford to use it any longer
we've got to have some kind of a shared
global identity now which
fiendish are difficult derrick um you
know and a lot of these philosophers
of the 20th century realized this after
the atomic bomb in 1945 and spent
an awful lot of time and energy on
trying to re-explore conscient models
for that hegelian models for that
old mystical spiritual traditions for
that to try to see if we could unify
humanity
and of course we also have another
ambition here which is echotopianism
which is just environmentalism plus
it is to develop the civilization that
can handle a sustainable planet
which then has access to the
technologies that enables that to happen
so echotopianism and cosmopolitanism and
possibly synthesis are just
isms we now invent for people to play
start
playing with these bigger ideas to them
pull them down
put them into your own meditative
contemplative practices
and then start building communities from
that
that the only way you can do it yeah and
that's what you're saying
right when you when you first work in
penis's work
yeah but our work like the work of
ivarka peterson and butterscotch
we all tie into one another greg
enriquez is doing this in america right
now trying to completely redefine what
psychology is
okay so we're all working on sort of
systemic thinking and
jordan hall obviously does this and
dennis macenberger do this too so
there's a lot of guys out there trying
to work on new
larger models or systems that we can
think
to then but then we have to be activists
and actually have to implement them and
that starts with their own
personal spiritual practice it starts
there
and then who else lives nearby to you so
you can share the experience
one or two mornings every every week and
share meditate to contemplative
practices
that's the building of a congregation
starts there then that congregation can
get socially involved in the
neighborhood where you live
well to start where you've got tons of
psychiatry patients lining up who need
more than just psychiatric help right
so yes so so that that's that's how i
see it going forward
yeah yeah no i it's here i think though
there's there's a challenge because um
my sense at least
is that the ears that are at least
interested to hear what we're speaking
about are not
um you're not likely to find them around
your actual physical location unless you
move somewhere
where there happen to be clusters
already gathering
so the people that i connect with most
around these kind of ideas not that i
can't have conversations with lots of
people but people that are more
committed to
um contemplating these things together
are in fact from all locations in the
world and of course that's when we are
speaking about the kind of um
city in some sense as a digital city
now there's still something to tie back
in here and this is something that
jordan hall was speaking about with his
civilian project he was on the podcast a
few episodes ago
and we're seeing this movement toward or
at least an interest in smart
villages future thinkers are building
one of these it's definitely within
this solar system of thinking in terms
of how can we live together well in an
embodied sense
but participate in the online commons
and market and
be innovative because we're living so
well together and taking care of
ourselves
practicing things together we can be
more generative and you know you can see
how
those things kind of work my sense is is
that
at least with the voicecraft project
voicecraft collective is that
shared experiences of um of meaningful
dialogue so john viveki's talking about
dialogos of course
um the key thing for me in the years of
this project has always been be part of
transformative conversations that's my
own personal bias in here of course
but what we're experimenting with at
least is how can we in fact come
together
and tune into a kind of shared
exploration and integration not just
about these themes but you can
begin to form connections begin to
contemplate things like integrity and
emergence and whatever it is and um
i think this is a key thing like forming
connections in a sort of metacultural
space having access to move between
different communities
online where there are protocols
developed for interaction
that is like a shared almost you could
say ritual i think more like ceremony
where we can know how to
connect with the people we actually can
most
benefit from connecting with but still
be
in some sort of resonant touch with
a way of integrating these big picture
perspectives of where we are
with some of the more like real physical
dynamics of our time how can we find the
people to do things
locally with i think is is an
interesting question and i think the
relationship between
both is important absolutely uh i'll
give you an example the center book was
greatly inspired by burning man
and burning man stopped being a major
event for 80 000 californians in the
nevada desert already
30 years ago when he started expanding
across the world
so larry harvey's vision for burning man
was that this would be way too
vulnerable
it was all about the nevada festival and
that's why we basically set up a model
with just 10 simple principles
that anybody in the world was allowed to
copy and as long as they copied and
reported back to birmingham headquarters
they were even given a certificate like
you're an official burn
now there are thousands of burns around
the world and i've helped out a lot here
in europe because in europe we've
experimented and
invented new formats like urban burn and
things like that like smaller
formats were a lower threshold for
people to participate for the first time
because to me when i came to burning man
it are all the qualities of a new
spiritual movement
i know yeah it is wealthy white
californians
go there we don't even have to get
started but again i expect elites who
can't afford to to start the new ideas
first
for them the idea is to to you know
spread wider
sometimes great ideas come from the
bottom up too but sometimes they
actually come top
bottom but with burning man it was clear
that you can go at least for eight days
and live in a temporary communist utopia
where we ban money
and you you are self-reliant you take
care of yourself and here are the simple
rules you need to follow for that to
happen
and for example we got an event here in
scandinavia called the borderland
and the borderland this year if it had
happened corona stopped it will happen
next year
but 6 000 people gathered without a
single
person we professionally employed
full-time to work on the event
it's so flat in its structure that six
thousand people
can manage to live together for eight
days and create a really fantastic event
together
without nobody getting paid anything
okay
i love those ideas right now because
again all of these
sort of proto-spiritual ideas we see
right now call them spiritual prototypes
the smart villages are certainly
included that but anything you do
anywhere in the world today that
works will become a story and sooner it
becomes the story the brilliant thing
with human beings is that they're great
at mimicking
they mimic bad stuff when they've got
nothing else to mimic they may make
terrible advertising and start smoking
cigarettes if they get nothing better to
mimic
but when they get great things to mimic
that's what they prefer human beings
have a liking
towards mimic constructive ideas so if
somebody
implements an idea like this and not
just talks like we guys are doing right
now
but actually implements an idea like
this like say builds a digital monastery
in france or australia in sweden right
now
that is augmented meaning it also has a
physical department and a building and a
house somewhere where
people can move and go into deep studies
and meditation practice and things like
that
like monasteries used to be these
monasteries are going to come back in a
big
way because people have such a great
need for them and
every one of them is then an example for
others to look at
and i think the role modeling aspects of
what important
if you move towards some kind of
ideological
hierarchy like okay you have to believe
this and this and this
well then we're going to kill it
instantly and if it's all about
you have to learn how to listen properly
to others and not use the wrong words
but you do have to learn how to listen
properly to others though
you do but if you go into tonality and
etiquette before you go into substance
you're done
that's exactly what the woke movement is
done and that's why it's failing on a
massive scale
because at the end of the day substance
such as sustainability of the planet
uh does this work do we take
responsibility for the budget actually
things cost money
you know we are surrounded in a
commercial world we're surrounded by
commercial world that we have to have a
relationship
towards uh do we make sure that the
right people get in through the gate and
actually that there's a way to throw
people out that shouldn't have been her
in the first place
or are we just naive and hippie it
should let everybody in and then fail
okay so all of these i think i think all
of these things have to be attended to
and what i said is that yes you have to
learn how to listen to other people
otherwise you go stupid
actually not only that you have to learn
how to people who disagree with you
which we call antagony beautiful word
because otherwise you end up in an echo
chamber and we learn what that is the
last 10 years you become stupid
but we also know that they're very hard
to resolve unless there's a certain
artfulness in interaction
and capacity to be able to take another
perspective
that can only really come if there's a
capacity to regulate oneself and so
there's this dynamic interaction between
capacity to listen and capacity to
regulate oneself
so this is where the feminism comes
between the feminine and the masculine
there that you're exactly no no i don't
i don't i don't even think it's that i
don't think that's feminine or
that's just passive or open aggression
you're talking about in the case it goes
wrong
no i think this is if you look back at
the into the last 30 years and look at
forums that have existed for 30 years
and i'm a member of a couple of those
myself
they were all well moderated they had a
set of rules you need to follow like
burning man
and they were moderated somebody kept
check of who walked in who walked out
and how things were conducted and so you
got a code of conduct within that
environment
it's quite easy actually it's just that
you need it you can't just
you know say oh we started this thing
and anybody wants to conjoin because
i totally agree with you facebook forums
that fail yeah right so we know that we
know that we have that experience after
30 years again
role modeling look at anybody who
successfully moderated the forum for 30
years and learn from them
well yeah so a forum obviously is true
that there's a kind of
a solipsistic aspect to this like
circling thing where
people get together and they circle
around their emotions over and over and
over again
um and and there's no real content there
often it's just
and people think have all these
emotional openings and experiences and
then after after that it's like
you know what have we what have we
really learned here
um so there i don't know there has to be
i think uh there has to be some logos to
if that's the correct word in into the
mix
i agree it's it's a dynamic interaction
i mean so um
yeah like okay so so let me let me
put a few perspectives on the table then
i'm really interested to see how you
guys connect these ideas um
so okay so the first one something that
you discuss in your book as well
alexander in
referencing ian mcgillcrist although you
don't
reference him to sort of support that uh
exactly the medical research
shows that the left hemisphere is for
this and the right hemispheres but this
but as metaphors
um so it's kind of interesting i wrote
my
really terrible quality master's
dissertation i called it part making
hole making and process
um and for me i did i i wrote i wrote it
don't
be so depressively degrading you wrote a
great thesis no no it was [ __ ] i'll tell
you why it was [ __ ] because
so i went to uh university of bristol
for the masters which is a philosophy of
like a
one of the top philosophy of science
universities and that wouldn't have been
my choice i made it for personal reasons
at the time it was just
economically viable it's where my
girlfriend at the time was going and
it was you know whatever so but that's
not my temperament as a philosopher
though i'm interested in analytic
clarity and i do my best i'm more of the
continental kind of persuasion but even
putting that aside i'm interested in a
kind of more um
i'm interested in philosophy as life and
philosophy
not only right i was interested in
phenomenology but i was very interested
in psychedelics i was very interested in
psychedelics and the recognition that
the patterns that were important to
discuss were things that were to be
essentially enacted in the world and now
i couldn't cram them not only that but i
couldn't cram them into the kind of
formulaic way that so i failed essays
because i wasn't
wasn't presenting them in a way that
people wanted to see essays presented so
as a compromise i had to present things
in a way which took away a lot of the
creative enjoyment for me and so it's on
that basis that
i say it was a [ __ ] [ __ ] essay and also
because well
for other things too but anyway part
making homemaking and process
the idea broadly speaking of we have
this analytical
style so bertrand russell spoke about
the mystical impulse and the scientific
impulse
it's something like this it's something
that's interested in um
seeing things and how they fit together
once you've already taken
a gestalt and want to sort of dissect it
to see if there's consistency
and then there's the capacity to
actually integrate and open up and to
have a different kind of of vision
um to feel one's connectedness to things
and to sort of intuit
patterns and how things fit together and
i think as cognitive styles we can tend
towards one or the other
and alexander you speak about philosophy
as being something which toes the line
between both of these and that's a
smaller percentage of the population
and so you know broadly speaking and
this is not
exactly precise language but i kind of
like it i think about it in terms of
thinking and feeling
now it's not just thinking of me i'm b
you have to be you have to be charitable
with me um with these terms
now vocabulary used and provoked for
varkivit is that i basically said that
we're going to talk about narratives
there are fundamentally three different
narratives
and our hemispheres make two of them one
is called logos the other is called
pathos
and logos is your thinking and pathos is
your feeling and the mythos
the story we tell about ourselves is the
attempt to unify the two that's why the
myth
is tied to the sense of self so i use
logos paths and myths in a very
simplified way actually to describe
these things
exactly what you're talking about okay
okay
so broadly we have these different
cognitive styles some people might tend
towards one more than the other
and maybe society even preferences them
for various reasons i mean you could
might look at autism and various things
and um
[Music]
the kind of engineering impulse in one
way or the artistic impulse in that
other people
can kind of grasp onto these things with
the question is okay
how do these dynamics as well as a
number of
other um
ways that we can tend as archetypal
dispositions
how can we include what would be
a fuller spectrum of cognitive style
and expressive capacity whether
in whatever artistic form but also
perceptual capacity how to
relate these things together in a kind
of group dynamic and there's one more
perspective i want to put to you here
and i think you'll enjoy it enjoy
riffing with it
and that's you speak about obviously um
so so you're
you're a nietzschean but also someone
who will say uh actually i want to do a
patricide on nietzsche
and part of which is beautifully
provocative okay is lovely
um and uh and you're serious about it in
an important regard and i'm not looking
to um speak to
the fullness of why you're serious about
that but one of the reasons is that you
recognize the importance that the the
over man of the future
so to so to say is not a man it's not
one person certainly not a man but
actually a
a group of people a collective that is
recognizes nevertheless the
identification there's individual
sovereignty but they but
the individual kind of dynamics of inner
development but also
the inter relationship so it's a
relational
philosophy again and so it's okay my
proposition would be then it's that
it's actually understanding the and and
in innovating in this new medium
um sourcing what our archetypal
dispositions
are through the course of evolution and
understanding how they're playing in the
new medium
but what's the right relationship of
interaction
as a people talk about collective
intelligence but here
i think intelligence depends what i mean
by intelligence but let's just go with
it what the right
interrelationship of these component
parts or individuals are so as to
be maximally innovative and actually do
this
thing of enacting the realization of
this shared mythos
which then becomes the thing that is
mimicked and in this way
i see a capacity for um
spreading on a much wider scale um
anyway so that's that's as an initial
proposition something like this
oh yeah i get it i get it uh we're
talking about um
an intelligent group of people that you
love to belong to
yeah we call it the gangs it's like
learning how to behave together with
four other guys your own age
and then you got the men's group and the
man scoped by men of different ages who
call each other out
but you have the different formats you
can work with and
uh i would say um two things the first
thing is that you need to find your own
archetype
and your own archetype usually has two
levels that's why we have majors and
minors when we go to college so
uh your first primary archetype is the
thing you do with ease
without even paying attention to it but
other people admiring you
and people often mistake this they often
think that they have to work hard
to get to their archetype i said no your
primary archetype is probably something
you just have lost for naturally
it's just something you're good at it's
like you know cooking walking the dog or
whatever it doesn't have to be that
advanced but something that other people
see you doing and say wow he's on fire
and he does that and does it really well
so the primary archetype is don't go too
far to find it find it very closely to
yourself
sometimes you inherit it from your
father your mother sometimes you don't
but you know it's
it's an archetype and if it's not from
one of your parents go find a mentor of
asset
find an older person preferably your own
gender not necessarily
who has that archetype and has developed
it fully who can then teach you
how you develop it then you got a
secondary archetype too which
we should point out the secondary
archetype is this is something you're
good at if you
if somebody has to be so say somebody's
looking for somebody with a specific
primary archetype and nobody shows up
then you say okay i'm not an expert at
it but i worked on it and i got certain
talents for it so i can take on that
responsibility temporarily
and that's when you get challenged to
really grow when you go into a secondary
architect
developing these two archetypes before
you're 25 years old and you're
lucky that's a really good start in life
that's what education should give you
that is what your surroundings your
family should give you that it's
certainly what your best friends and
your social
media should give you before you're 25
years old if you have those
then you next discover that your
archetype because you're younger your
archetype is the archetype of energy
younger not a wisdom yet because the
archetype of wisdom is the one you get
when you've done it for years you do it
one hand and
yeah it's the easiest thing in the world
because i've done it so many times
before and you can actually become a
teacher of it
you can become a role model of it
because you can be that when you're
older
and you have the wisdom of that
archetype when you're younger
you you have no idea how fun it is to be
a mentor it's wonderful to be older and
to be a teacher and to be good at
something at least and
and be able to teach it and pass it on
to somebody younger and see how they try
to do it and put tons of energy into it
and they do it more energetically and
even more creatively
than you do as the wise man because
because they are having to do it in a
novel way they just don't do it the same
way all over
this is the love between generations i'm
looking for a spiritual work
now if you then put that into the group
context it could certainly work what's
important here
is to not go into a group of people
where people are just sort of lazy and
almost an infinite way join the group
to avoid hard work spirituality is
always hard work
otherwise it isn't spirituality so
somebody says that oh we're just going
to get some people together and
you're going to sit here in circle and
here's a little crystal or something you
can hold your hand and pass on to the
next guy you talk about your feelings
all the time
then you've got to remember that before
you do spiritual work there's a
very simple principle and that is
spiritual work
always comes in three steps you can ask
any shaman in peru
you and i are into psychedelics tim and
i guess andrew is too at a certain
extent at least you and i are
okay you go and see the shamans you work
with them for a month
you really are the young guy because
these shamans are all they know [ __ ]
so they're wise and they adopt you and
you happy to be the young
archetype energetic version right you
learn from them you try to figure out
what they do
and you also try to figure out how could
i possibly take this women back to
europe and implement it to the west
right
would you learn from that the first
thing alone from sheamus is this
everything is done in three steps
number one is intention number two is
the ceremony
and number three is the integration and
this goes for group exercises too
even more so that's why i tell people if
you
if people call you and want you to join
the spiritual group of some kind of
gonna get together ask them what the
intention is
and then go to yourself and be tough on
yourself and look at your own intentions
at the moment
and if your intentions but you're at in
your spiritual work with yourself and
your own meditation contemplation
practice
has nothing to do what they're up to
then tell them so and said thank you for
the invite
good luck with everything i'm in a
different place right now because i can
see how my intention right now rhymes
with your intention
but if i'm wrong about your intention
please let me know so sit down with
people and ask them what the intention
is then you can conduct the circling or
the workshop
or the educational collaboration or or
the collaborative arts party like you do
to burning man
and then you can also enjoy integrating
it afterwards which you can do when you
leave that place you can do it online
you meet
three three weeks later and said wasn't
it fun to do this together yeah
this happened to me and that happened to
you and you know and and you can
integrate
so the next intention you take on with
the same group
is on a higher level now if you do that
if you think in tension ceremony
integration
then i'm all for group collaborations
then i always ask myself these days not
to waste time my time with anybody this
time is that
what is the intention here and i said
okay if i should have read a certain
book
or seen a certain film or studied
something before
this group gets together then i should
really do that i take responsibility for
that part of my intention is my
preparation for this work
because i'm not going to sit there and
pretend just by reading the wikipedia
article
and dropping a few names that understand
what you guys are talking about that's
just that just
that's just being deeply unserious about
spiritual work and
i think if people can get both the
archetype for
on their own level right and then look
at the mixing of archetypes which
which is a great group great group it's
a mixing arc a congregation is the full
full schema of archetypes that's
like a congregation religious
congregation is the imitation of the
tribe in its full glory
now if if we do that serious work then
i'm all for it yes i
i subscribe to all of these ideas but i
think it's really important to get
the grounding proper first properly
first
yeah i appreciate that thank you for
outlining that i um
i think it's really you know because
taking psychedelics is the same thing
you don't throw psychedelics into the
throat of a complete
unknown who's not prepared for it
absolutely preparation is everything
isn't it a preparation is the
intentional part right you have to do a
lot of preparation for stuff i think you
know
preliminary preparation all right i take
this
i take this very seriously but just to
um
recall something we said at the
beginning of this conversation something
you outlined in your
early um introduction alexander
was that well we are in the midst of a
paradigm shift
and there is much of the wisdom that got
us here
which must be recalibrated and sort of
taken forward and we can still be
informed by deep history i'm totally
with you i think it's deeply important
and
it's one of the reasons i love love your
work and appreciate the podcast and all
the rest of it
and at the same time there's also a
sense in which we're stepping into novel
terrain
my sense is the organization the
emergent organization of what archetypes
are in fact necessary and what's called
in us to be able to interact in these
new mediums
is itself there's something different
there or at least there could be
and if that's the case what then
for basically uh the experimentation as
far as it goes
is a work in progress let's put it like
that you know
so it's kind of like yes um
intention ceremony integration
absolutely
am i sure of what the most important
intentions are what all the archetypes
are what the ceremony precisely needs to
be
and also what the integration practices
are no i'm not sure about those things
um
but there's there's some stuff there and
i think this is where
the innovation needs to occur
sure yeah because i think i'll say okay
go ahead i just said i thought that
there's there's a kind of problem with
these sort of things when you get very
very ambitious and you try to
create some grandiose thing where where
the the people who
started birding man probably just a
couple guys like you know
like this thing that jesus says if two
or three people are gathered
in my name that's all you you really you
really need
on some level but yeah right i'm trying
to create this super structure
uh and be incredibly ambitious this
purely in the vision space this is
purely and what's conceptually possible
by by way and integrating that with
this uh dynamic that we've got going on
here which has the exodus on the one
hand and just how big is the separation
going to be
like my intentions are not
any more grandiose than is appropriate
to to have them and
that really is nested in the fact that
there's not a person
well there are people i meet who who i
am
wary that i cannot extend a hand of
interaction to in a way that's um not
you know aware of the fact it may not be
taken well or something like this but
for the most part you know i
a gathering of intelligent people
beautiful but but i also
i i know that there is a capacity to
remember what to care about and to hold
the space
of relational integrity that doesn't
require the kind of intellectual
capacity that can grasp and
vibrate up and down the full stack of
these ideas but nevertheless
knows what the [ __ ] to care about and
can tell if someone is not showing up
with integrity
this speaks to the kind of matriarchal
role perhaps as you describe alexander
in your work and what have you
but broadly speaking this like you know
i i don't
you know beautiful things are possible
when speaking with someone who is
has the appropriate open stance
where they're willing to stand in their
own truth and be
um and confrontational even if necessary
but who can then
ultimately as well surrender when it's
appropriate for them to accept the kind
of
flow of another and whether they have
much to add
it's like man we are obviously we're
creatures with a lineage of billions of
[ __ ] years the patent recognition and
the intuitive capacity for just
helping spark something is beautiful so
in my opinion there is
if there is the capacity to listen
deeply and well
and to make one's presence felt in a
situation
then then then there's something to add
to that collective
dynamic
yeah some of this is rhetoric and
rhetoric is a fantastic science in
itself i mean how do you speak properly
to other people how do you behave in a
certain environment how do you find out
the context before you enter the room
yeah yeah exactly no cue i called
preparation of invitation making
actually yeah
no i and and we live in a very heated
environment at the moment
but on the other hand i'm one of those
who who you know
i can behave in a very hot way on
twitter because i think the medium
itself
is that medium okay but i certainly
wouldn't behave the same way if i go to
her dinner party
so uh i i think i'm trying to experiment
just like everybody else's and i take
responsibility for the things i do and
i'll listen to constructive criticism at
all times and do all those things
i think of it as contextuality and
contextuality now means that we are so
many new
media so many new environments so many
new interfaces like this one
where on zoom we're doing a three zoom a
format that was only invented a few
months ago
and uh we're experimenting with it as we
go which we invented by the way no
yeah at least the word three soon yeah i
think
it's widespread now three zooms and
foursomes okay so
um but that's a new interface
it will require new rhetoric eventually
uh i just think
it's all again about a question of
timing so when do you jump to the
rhetoric
and and i'm i'm one of these people who
says that okay
if you go to the rhetoric too quickly
the problem is you will kill the
trickster
and this way jordan peterson agrees with
me says that if you go too quickly to
have to be saved in a certain way uh for
example that to me historically speaking
it's typical sort of little nervous
middle class behavior
it's just like okay don't use certain
words don't behave in certain ways
because it's impolite and somebody might
be offended
okay it always turns out that it's some
it's some middle class church lady who's
offended at all times right
so some people take two offense very
quickly and that is just
human it happens all the time but if you
learn from history
i'm one of these guys that says that
okay rhetoric is fantastic
absolutely needed and we will have to
reinforce rhetoric
it's called moderation and censorship
because we cannot have
all the floodgates open at all times and
then we're drenched in
you know violent child porn or whatever
evil man can come up with because man
can come up with tons of evil right
so we don't want that here right we
there's certain limits to what we do
we that's what we build we build a wall
around the community
and we have a clever guy who's
experienced who sits at the port
at the wall and decides who gets in who
gets out that's called membrane theory
every life form is dependent on it you
cannot let any
everybody into every life cell because
then all the cells die
same thing here and rhetoric is part of
that rhetoric is essentially
the 10 burning man principles it's
essentially they are the conditions for
everybody and they're all equal for
everybody who joins
they're all the same just to interject
um
you know i remember somebody saying in a
community that i was involved in it's
good to have a crazy person
there somehow like a fool or a madman or
if the community is too clean and and if
it's too
then then um yeah then then there
there has to be that dynamic of
disruption as well
uh uh other otherwise it becomes a very
sterile environment
we have them at immense events you know
who are talking first
we have a couple of these guys and the
guys go that guy is such a lunatic why
do you even allow him in it's just like
if he wasn't here we wouldn't have a
lunatic here
oh that'd be a lot worse yes thank you
so thank you for appreciating the joker
or the trickster roll and
this is what i'm concerned with is that
if we let
a certain middle-class behaviors that
we're comfortable with dictate our
social environments
then working-class people will be
excluded
people with different backgrounds will
be excluded because they will feed an
older part of it
and we will not be inclusive so to be
enclosed is that as long as we allow the
trickster in the room
to behave like an [ __ ] at times and
and be you know
and he after all fix this do not take
responsibility for what they do the only
archetype that is relieved of
responsibility for their own actions the
rest of us have to
the trickster is not okay if the
trickster is allowed to be in the room
uncomfortable that anybody can feel
welcome if they walk into the room as
long as they speak the same language
that is to me the lowest level rhetoric
i will have to
accept and especially in experimental
environments
so we foster people during the intention
process and the preparation process
this is going to be a tough ride not
tough in the sense that you'll be
you know intensely challenged you'll be
welcome to stay hang on in there
but there will be people around who will
start doing and saying things you never
thought you'd ever have to hear okay
but just allow that to happen let it
pass on and it's not you are responsible
take care of it because we have
moderators who do
so rather look at the moderators and how
they work and if they do that well
you've got
perfect role models for you to want to
become a moderator and make an even
better environment
and that's when rhetoric comes into the
picture not not too early but but at the
stage when you want to
lift the whole level and again it's part
of the intentional process
if part of the integration was it was a
good it was a good weekend we shared
together
but hey it was me and erin crueler and
nastier than he would have to be
a lot of that was just completely
unnecessary then it becomes part of the
next intentional process
to include more rhetoric in the mix
yeah and also i find when it's when the
atmosphere is
is there's something especially in
anglo-saxon culture
there there's there's this pathology of
nice you know being
being being there's kind of like
especially find it in the
british people they have they're very
nice and sweet and diplomatic with you
and they want everything to be
you know and then but there's a knife
and that you get in the back
afterwards right um there are hidden
knives
in an atmosphere that that's too um
yeah andrew and i [ __ ] about this we
talk about it
we talk about england but i think it's i
think it's very angle saxon i think like
um you know i think i think the rough
guys went to the colonies and therefore
much rougher
exactly that's this is that's us here
right now the
the the ones who escaped the the police
it's like the it's like the south
african peasants the south african
peasants i remember when i grew up at
least
there's no way they could revive an
essex wife's dinner in london you know
it's just like
yeah they'd be way too rough for that
environment but it's just that's
cultural difference yeah
yeah so yeah no this is uh this is
beautiful
i um i just want to check in how long do
we have
we're speaking for two hours we got a
little bit longer how are we feeling
yeah we can sort of start rounding it
off but it's been wonderful yeah
it's good
[Music]
so moving to australia at 11. you can
imagine like
i i sounded i wasn't um eaton
posh you know i didn't have the the
royal aristocracy
posh accent but i had the kind of
private school
london boys accent um
and uh you know you can still see that
come through a little bit but
my family wasn't of that kind of it
didn't come from that way my dad made um
you know enough enough money that he put
me in that school
and so you can imagine me going to
australia uh as
11 years old very very pale very very
posh
within the first week i had a broken
nose concussion my arm was broken
um and you know like it is beautiful and
uh
ever since then it's been an interesting
relationship for me to
immediately get a sense of how to relate
to
you can say the kind of the working
class australian
hyper masculinist tendency of those
group dynamics and i still sound like i
sound
so i'm immediately still taken to the
other but generally speaking i like
playing with it and have quite a bit of
fun with it so
yeah it's it's it's important to um
i i really appreciate all the dynamics
we've spoken to here
um the inclusion of the trickster very
important
yeah and you still do the hums
not as often as prince andrew does
though but
i feel like i come from i think for me
like i feel almost the opposite
experience i come from kind of
you know uh well just middle class
canada
is is it's kind of it's kind it has a
roughness to it right
and then i come to france and france
everything is artificial manners and
you know there is a kind of uh you know
emotional honesty
in france but but uh but it's like
moving from non-artifice to artifice
you know what you're describing is sort
of the opposite going from artifice to
and i sort of moved from australia to
canada because i moved from south africa
to scandinavia
and i do go to england and i've been
working in england for
i've been working in london for the last
30 years but there's nothing in me that
wants to move there i
love being in london i love seeing my
friends and hang out with them but i
don't want to move there
i just it's just not my taste it's just
not my thing
mm-hmm beautiful all right guys
well i'm feeling pretty good with this i
want to ask you one more question though
attention
so when you talk about this
there obviously is like a major
grassroots movement
um it doesn't want to fall into the old
trap that we call new age
yeah it wants to take spirituality
seriously
it wants to have a spirituality which is
compatible with science
in the best possible way it wants a
spirituality that is interested in all
spiritual traditions it doesn't turn its
back on christianity or judaism or islam
or anything you just
research them all and it's sort of
very welcoming in that sense and it's
digitally savvy and i think it's
happening already in the uk
the us certainly in scandinavia we're
seeing it
in europe too it seems to be bottom up
which is very healthy right so it's it's
it's meant to be learned from and role
model in the prototyped
rather than it's being dictated and i
don't think anybody would step forward
today if a varick or a hall or
goddammit and alexander barbara step
forward and say this is how you must
conduct your spirituality they would
just be laughed at for good reasons
right
this is this is a this is a moment that
really wants to be bottom up but where
do
where do you see it going over the next
five ten years where where do you see
you have the growth aches and pain aches
and where does it come through very
quickly right now
yeah um a big question for me is
um my roots in australia and whether or
not there is something
ripe here to build and i haven't given
up on that and over the next couple
months it's something i want to put um
more energy into i've been involved a
lot more paying attention to the things
worldwide
[Music]
um
well speaking to the australian context
what i see is that there's well this is
broader as well there's this
relationship between um
spiritual spirituality and entrepreneurs
where there's a sort of interaction
between spirituality and the market
that i am skeptical of i don't think it
is this grassroots that you're actually
speaking to
i'm particularly interested in coming
into more clarity about the relationship
between spirituality and the commons and
spirituality and the market
and i'm i mean the kind of
sustainability
that i see will come from real
relationships based in an understanding
of a sort of in touchness with
with with fellowship
friendship there's nature-based
shamanism that's for sure there's a big
movement towards connecting with nature
in australia
which is very interesting and there's a
big psych and there's the psychedelic
stuff as well
the psychedelic stuff can have a lot of
the new age
lack of rigor in it and of too much of a
focus sometimes
on purely the therapy um
so there's that that i'm i'm looking for
more integration
with a kind of more uh
let's say kind of um
can i get can i give you two terms here
you could play with
one is the guru weekend you go off and
you pay
you pay a lot of money to see a guru for
a weekend and then you
left back in your previous life right
after
and the other one is congregation
congregation is the way nobody makes
money out of
nobody else but you do meet on a regular
basis and you create a spiritual
community together
those are those are the two extremes i
see right yeah yeah yeah
that's nice it's that sense australia is
very similar here
to to europe and for example
psychedelics are moving into
spirituality the question is it's going
to be the congregation that takes care
of that
or is it just going to be these gurus
who give you psychedelics and you pay
you pay 3 000 for a long weekend with
them where is that gonna end up
yeah um well we're gonna see both and
so my in some sense my response is that
the digital interaction actually needs
to be
like what i'm the vision that i've
wanted to be part of creating has always
been
to establish a kind of um authentic and
integris
field of interaction where you can have
it's like okay you're doing it in this
way come step into this come step into
this space
speak your peace like you'll be heard
and addressed
and we can have confrontation we can do
all the rest of it the answer is i kind
of don't know
my personal interest is in the
congregation
style i'm skeptical of gurus in general
i think as a philosophical point
i've spent quite a lot of time listening
to and like
contemplating someone like adida for
instance
um and i am very very skeptical of
someone placing themselves
beyond you you should be having satsang
together in some important sense right
that you have to come have satsang with
me and i'm your portal
it's like all right big man let's see
then okay i don't know
so i'm more on the side of the
congregation to be honest with you
we had that problem here in europe this
year and there were so many of the older
men who got so tired in men's work of
just doing it for free
and professionally trained therapists
and things like that so we decided to
split the movement but make it very
clear
that there's we call it the manifesto
network which is a network of men who do
men's events around europe and it works
wonderfully it's flat in structured
decentralized work for four years nobody
gets paid but then we also started a
manifesto core this year which is
essentially an
agency for appointed you know formal
advisors and therapists and things who
do men's work but do professionally and
they will charge you some
for doing the work they do because
they're replacing other therapists and
professional work and things like that
i think it has to be this sort of
division between the two that's why i
love the burning man movement because
eventually at the end of the day you had
to employ a few people at birmingham at
headquarters in san francisco to keep
the machine together
you gotta have some people in their work
full-time like you've got to have a
priest or a pastor in your congregation
you got to pay somebody to do the work
you don't pay them a lot but you pay
them so they can do it professionally
right
but the rest of the work is all
supporting one another in your spare
time
outside of work and that's exactly why
it goes so deeply spiritual
and i think to define these the
congregation
versus the commercial activities i think
the problem with new age was that it
ended up as nothing but these guru
weekends
it was it was just a marketplace where
he's like buy this crystal here and
buy this stuff here go to see this guru
here and you have to pay a lot for it
to have somebody take you through portal
or whatever and
we know that's not spirituality that's
just
the best stuff is is you just find
somewhere in an
odd place and it's free you know you
hardly pay anything for it and it's
has way more actual value than the the
guy who's charging uh
you know thousands of euros an hour
to to to do satsang with them or
whatever the hell
yeah i tried to work with those things
that's why i'm getting involved with the
hackers in europe so that goes if they
like me or not
but burners and the men's movement and
the hackers these are three movements
that have emerged
they already exist i don't have to be
one of the innovators of them
they already exist they fascinate me
they're flat in structure
and they work towards a common shared
goal which is way bigger than any
personal goal could ever be
like fixing the men so the women have
some men to marry like men's movement
burners it's just like exploring the
possibility of creating
temporary communist utopias and go into
that experience as a full-on spiritual
exercise where everybody else is there
needs this as much as you do
and everybody else is there is there
without getting paid for it that that's
a deeply spiritual experience
and the same thing with the hackers
because today if you look at the world
politically
fighting communist china's dictatorship
is probably the coolest thing you can do
you can't be anything cool than a
taiwanese hacker who tries to get
through chinese censorship
and i think hackers again they're doing
this in their spare time they're doing
it for the love it they're doing it
because it is a good thing to do
that's what right is that's what the
word amateur means it means in italian
it means to do what you love or it's
like
to love what you do so it's like an
amateur activity where you're motivated
you have a pure motivation right
you don't have a mixed motivation you're
not trying to
seduce or you know somebody else do you
mean that i have to stop calling myself
an amateur [ __ ] now
yeah you're you're a professional thing
that's interesting so maybe just a nod
to a future conversation
might be to um discuss the
i'm very interested in your thoughts
about hierarchy you mentioned
flat structure i can't speak to this
stuff with um
articulate language but in the in an
image the image in my mind
is is not a flat structure but something
like a wave right that can
come together and have um
discernible uh
teacherly authority or
individuals who can disseminate wisdom
and of course this is something i know
you agree with it
flows into the rest of our conversation
you've got the people who have the
knowledge they've got the skills they
have your particular archetypes
so how can we lead and follow it's like
a dance hey where one leads at one time
one follows that another and how can we
have
the capacity to discern when to you know
embody which role and it doesn't look
like a flat thing it looks like a
it looks like a wave to me looks like
something dynamic
yeah we could call the good microherikis
if you prefer that word i i'm not scared
of the word heroic individuals why not
it's a great word it's just like
patriarchy is a great word you just have
met jorge next to it for god's sake
it's mad turkey that was lacking it
wasn't patrick it was too much of
so take back these words and redefine
them i used the word god in my work i
just put god into the future
if god doesn't exist yet then he could
certainly or she
whatever could exist in the future so
let's take back these words and
use them again and for example i used
during a conversation i talked about
wisdom and energy and the relationship
between the older the
the older mentor and the young mentee so
in the mentorship relationship of course
there's there are two hierarchies
one here is the heritage wisdom the
older
mentor is supposed to know more within
that archetype and therefore teach and
lead
the younger person but the younger
person has inherited
energy so what you contribute to any
environment you're in
you're at the top of that hierarchy so
if you cook the food in a group of
people
you're at the top of the food hierarchy
because you're responsible for the
kitchen you cook the food
that's hierarchy that's what hierarchy
is hierarchy is the way
an emergent collective
quickly organized itself into different
archetypes
so it's a yes it's a natural process
it's a natural
yeah yeah it will happen quite quickly
and and
what i mean with flat it's that the sums
overall are flat in the sense that
nobody has an officially dominant
position where they can say yes or no to
everybody else
so what you do for example if you're on
a large flat network of 500 men in
europe all work with men's events and
men's work
and that's a lot of very you know
bullheaded men there
the way you do it that's you basically
point a few guys to be moderated so the
group and place them on a slightly
higher level because they actually have
an authority that other guys don't have
but you're aware of that and that's all
you need to do to keep the rest of the
hierarchy as flat as you
as you can because you think that
organization
works best when it's decentralized and
it very often turns out to be the case
when you go
going to compare cultures and compare
examples
and compare role modeling that's when
it's great to have a decentralized
network but when you're just going to
implement an order so we're going to
have to build this building now
you don't wanna have people sitting
around forever circling talk about their
feelings no you want them to get up
each take their responsibility for the
thing they've been appointed to do and
then go off and do it so the building
gets built
that's different that's a different type
of hierarchy
yeah beautiful i'm interested the
relationship between uh the moderator
and the shaman can you speak to that at
all are these
like are these different in your
analysis
in your view yeah moderator is priestly
meaning it's shamanic but inside the
tribe
okay sheamus prefer to be outside
everything
you find them living in the forest
cooking witch's brews most of the time
they take tons of drugs they often die
young and they experiment with
themselves their surroundings in the
most hideous ways and that's exactly why
they're
shamanoids they call them shamanoid is
actually the psychological term for
shamanic people so
we expect about four percent of the
population to strong characteristics
that are called
chaminade these are people that are
often better off outside in the forest
living away from society
they have been idolized over the last
say 50 to 100 years way more than they
expected to that's why we have
dying rock stars as role models which i
think was a terrible idea to be honest
about it even if it was fun
okay but the shamanic characters are
like that but when the shamans work
within the tribal environment
and put on a robe a priest is
essentially one of the shamans
who takes on a robe to go into the
community to take on shamanic
responsibilities and shamanic is always
go between
the his goal between between tribes is
between man and the gods and it's going
between between men and women
and then it's called androgynous people
that's what androgynous characters are
similar to shamanic characters and
they're another four percent of the
overall population
so these tiny minorities the androgynous
caste and the shamanic cast are people
we should really care about in our
community
but we should also put them in the right
place and not idolize them as a norm for
everybody else
that's exactly why the lgbt movement
went overboard in the last 20 years
when instead of fighting for its own
rights and being proud of itself it
started to react like everybody had to
be
like them that that that is exactly
where things start to go wrong
so i am totally pro androgynous cast
totally pro-shamanic cast work and these
people in my work
adamant about it too but when the
shamans or the androgynous people take
on robes
to live within the community of the
inner circle or the outer circuit
the matriarch of the patriarchy which
are the dominant modes of society
then they can come become for example a
moderator and a moderator is why it's a
person with experience
it could be tough when needed and who's
not invested
in the value of the group so it cannot
be corrupted
that's a good moderator always appoint
the person
who's been around for a while seen this
and that and can take on that
responsibility listen i'll take it on
i'll be the moderator next year you can
decide whether i did a good job or not
and elect me again or pick somebody else
but i'm going to be here for a year i'm
going to moderate this group
and because i'm not too much invested in
the group itself
then i'm a good moderator otherwise
you're picking a guru and it becomes a
sec leader
and you got a sect and you don't
actually have a thriving community
that's the problem so another thing with
the moderator
pick several have a few of them we trust
each other but they have different
backgrounds different cultures different
genders
uh you know they can represent the
outside world in different ways and
that's when you get a good mix of
moderators and the bigger the forum gets
the more moderators you need
yeah beautiful thank you andrew
alexander it's been
really bloody nice to have this
conversation i've been really looking
forward to it thank you so much
for being here incredible conversation
thank you so much yeah it goes three
ways
yes thank you so much
[Music]
you